<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The reasons for vvhich the most illustrious and most potent prince, and lord, Lord Gustavus Adolphus, King of the Svvethens, Gothes and Vandals, great Prince of Finland, Duke of Esthonia and Carelia, and Lord of Ingria, vvas at length forced to march vvith an army into Germany</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02406</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12535</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119067</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854274</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854274</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19684</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02406)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19684)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1103:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The reasons for vvhich the most illustrious and most potent prince, and lord, Lord Gustavus Adolphus, King of the Svvethens, Gothes and Vandals, great Prince of Finland, Duke of Esthonia and Carelia, and Lord of Ingria, vvas at length forced to march vvith an army into Germany</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by A. Clouting], according to the copie of Stralsound,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Delft] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of the Dutch original.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gustaf --  II Adolf, --  King of Sweden, 1594-1632 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19684:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19684:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Reaſons</hi> For vvhich the moſt <hi>Jlluſtrious and moſt potent Prince, and LORD, LORD</hi> Guſtavus Adolphus,</p>
            <p>King of the Svvethens, Gothes and Vandals, great Prince of Finland, Duke of Eſthonia and Carelia, and Lord of Ingria, vvas at length Forced to March vvith an army into Germany.</p>
            <p>Printed according to the copie of Stralſound. Anno 1630.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:19684:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19684:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is an ancient proverbe, that no man is able to inioy peace, any longer, then it pleaſeth his neighbour: how true this is his Ma: off Swethen hath, to his great dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madg proved, in theſe yeares, and doth yet daily: for hombeit, it was his cheefecare and indevour, in all the time of his Raigne, to keepe inviolable Frindſhip with all his neighbours, and eſpecially, with the States of Germany; that peace and tranquillity might flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh on every ſide, and that trade, Comerce, and all oth repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aceable indevours, might be exercized, to the mutuall good off all Nations: yet could he obtaine nothing more, then that, by ſome haters of the publick peace, after that thay had waſted almoſt all Germany with fire and ſworde, greater ſnares were laid, from yeare to yeare, againſt his ſecurity. his Ma: was advertiſed long ago, and that, not of a few States of Germany, to provide for himſelf more maturely, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le this flame was yet ſpreading it ſelf in Germany, and that he should not think, thay would be more favourable or frindly to him, if thay were admitted to aproach nearer; but that he would then, preſently, take Armes, come into Germany, and with common forces, quench the common burning, being aſſured, that his owne cauſe was then in hand, when kis neighbours howſe was a burning. neither was there then wanting to his Ma: either excellent occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, his ſubiects inviting him, or iuſt cauſe, his oppreſſed friends and Allies ſo earneſtly requiring aide and ſuccour. but ſtill hoping, that at lenth, thay would prove more equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, then ſo impotently to inſult, over their harmles
<pb facs="tcp:19684:3"/>
Neighbours, meaſuring their manners, according to his own nature, he choſe rather to committ his own ſecurity for a while, to the goodnes of god and an innocent Conſcience, then raſhly therin to attempt any thing.</p>
            <p>But when in the yeare 1626. by reaſon of his own warr, which paſſed betweene him and the King and common wealth of Pole, he was marching into Pruſſia, a Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of the Kingdom off Pole, perceiving more narrowly, what he might promiſe himſelf, of thoſe foreſaid waſters and ſpoilers of Germany, he found his friends admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to be ſo farr, from being vaine, that the nearer his eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes approached to theſe Baltick provinces of Germany, ſo manny the more and greater occaſions of warre he percei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ved to be ſowen by them dayly, even againſt him: for in the firſt place, violating the law of Nations, thay intercep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his Ma. letters ſent to the Prince of Tranſilvania, ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them, and of malice againſt his Ma. publiſhed them with a fained interpretation, caſting withall his meſſenger into priſon; then alſo, howbeit there was oftentimes no ſmall hope, of redreſſing and, compoſing of the long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>troverſy, betwixt Swethen and Polland, by frind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly treaties, the Commiſſaries of both kingdomes meeting from yeare to yeare, yet theſe enimyes of common peace, cauſed, by their reiterated meſſengers and letters to Polland, that no peace ſhould be made with Swethen, vntill ſuch time, as thay had accompliſhed their determinations in the Romane Impire; putting the Polonians in hope, the States of Germany being once ranged in order, thay ſhould then haue them no ſlow aiders and aſſiſters to ſubdue Swethen.</p>
            <p>And to the end thay might effectuat, in deede, what by word thay promiſed: and that ſo farr as in them lay, thay might both deprive Swethen of all meanes, and ſtrengthen the Pole, thay did not only prohibit all exportation of Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers and Armes, out of Germany, to the King off Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then,
<pb facs="tcp:19684:3"/>
leaving withall the ſame free vnto the Polonians, then his enimyes; but alſo, when this ſeemed a ſmall matter, and thay perceived, notwithſtanding hereof, that abundance off ſouldiers did flock, to the moſt illuſtrious King off Sweth. not only from other parts, but alſo (and that againſt their wills) out of Germany it Self, the yeare next following, 1627 thay ſent the Duke off Holſatia againſt his Ma. with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> great Army, into Pruſſia, and that not, vnder his own, or vnder the Poles; but vnder the Colours off the Emperour of Rome himſelff.</p>
            <p>Neither content with this koſtility; but that alſo thay might vtterly ſeclude the kingdom off Sweth: from all Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ague of ſociety with mankinde: thay did not only wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſpoile the innocent ſubiects of his Ma. arriving at the coaſt off Germ. for Commerce, taking their goods by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, and confiſcating their ſchipps: but alſo, thay did mainely effectuat that, at Lubick and the reſt of the townes off the vandalls, by their Scouts, ſent out, in ſhew, that thay might reſtraine trading to theſe townes only; but in very deede, that thay might withdraw the ſame, from the ſubiects off the kingdom of Swethen, and that by this occaſion, thay might gather together ſchipps, and a Navie, by which, thay might belch out this venom, conceaved in their minds, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the Baltick ſea it ſelf; as in the yeare next following, thay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id manifeſtly ſchew, by the monſtrows titles off General<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity off the ſea coaſts, and by taking in poſſeſſion, as well the Land places and Fortifications, as the Coaſts, and have<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of Mechlinburgh and Pomer, with the acts enſewing theron.</p>
            <p>Let any man, who is able, Iudg, that all theſe things perhaps ought to haue bin tollerated, and for avoyding off curioſity in other mens affaires, to haue bin paſſed by in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, while thay kept them-ſelves as yet, vpon the Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, oppoſit to Sweth: yet certainly, after thay were exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the ſea it ſelff, by chooſing the Haven off the Sound
<pb facs="tcp:19684:4"/>
for a receipt of their Piracy; by how much the more this was done, to the great preiudice off all the States, who, by any neceſſity what ſoever, did depend vpon this Sea; ſo much the les ought it to haue bin tollerated by his Ma. off Sweth: eſpecially, ſeing the iuſt protection off this ſea was off ould, peculiar, to the Kings off Sweth.</p>
            <p>Therfore, ſo manny iniuries alſo being added to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer advertizement off Friends, when his Ma. (being now ſo much the more wary) in the ſpring off the yeare, 1628. was againe paſſing over to Pruſſia, being carefull off no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, more, then that he might remedy theſe incommodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, by ſome honeſt meanes; it fell out that the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors off the towne off Stralſound did come vnto his Ma. in Pruſſia; who did heavily complaine, that, allthough their harmleſs citty, had committed nothing, either againſt the Roman Imperour, or againſt the Impire it ſelff, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any State off the Impire, for which it was ſo farr, that it was at any time Cited, or Accuſed, or convicted, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned; that even by an Emperial decree, it was declared innocent, and ſecured off withdrawing off the Army, which beſiedged it: yet ſuch was ye iniquity off that noiſom army; that, vilipending their innocency, neglecting the laws and conſtitutions, off the Empire, contemning the Contract, made, with thoſe off Pomer at, Arnhem, and not regarding manny other Covenants, made at divers ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, (by all which it might ſeeme, thay were ſinceerely ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured) neither conſidering the great ſommes off mony, vniuſtly exacted, and paid; with gifts and preſents; violating the very ſanctity, both off religious and common peace: it did firſt, waſt the Neighbouring villages off the Citty, it did build divers fortes, vpon the territories off the towne, it did fortify the Ile of Benholm, lying neare vpon the haven, to the preiudice of the towne; after it had taken it, by treac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hery, without any denunciation of enmity: it ſeaſed vpon
<pb facs="tcp:19684:4"/>
all paſſages; from the continent, to the Ile off Rugg, and from the towne to the continent, and back, from the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to the towne, it did vex the Citticens, with divers ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous treaties, and having exhauſted them by great tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, it chardged them alſo with Garriſons, and ſo, deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the haven it ſelf, with their ſchipps and munition: and at lenth, all theſe being denied them, by their priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged liberty, it did preſs the towne it ſelff with a ſtrait Siedge, and did perſecute it, moſt vnworthily, to the very laſt, with fire and ſword. Whenas therfore, the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours decrees, did here effectuat nothing; the moſt Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Duke off Pomer, would not help them; when thay were eſteemed, as left of all the ſociety off the Hanſe townes: according to the Law, and cuſtom off Nations, by favour off their priviledges, by example off their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors, being compelled, to implore the aide off a Forrain Power, vntill that ſuddain tempeſt off warr, ſhould lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve raging; thay did accept, for a while, the Garriſons off the moſt Illuſtrious King off Denmark, as moſt ready to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell the ſuddennes off the firſt aſſault: yet, leaſt that ſchould turn to their future preiudice, as if thay had aſſociated them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, with the Emperours enimies; at laſt thay found no more equitable, and preſent remedy, then to commit their oppreſſed liberty, to the tuition, off the moſt Illuſtrious King off Swethen, as to a newtrall, and friendly King.</p>
            <p>The moſt illuſtrious King off Sweth: therfore, Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, in the firſt place, that thay could promiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves, no more favour, from ſo vnſatiable attemps, off an army, noted with ſo many hoſtilities; and next, marking, that the deſires off this afflicted citty, were grounded, vpon divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne and humane laws; as alſo, conſidering that bond off ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance, vicinity, common religion, liberty and commer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, by which that Citty was allway adicted, both to his Anceſtors, the moſt Illuſtrious Kings, and Kingdom of
<pb facs="tcp:19684:5"/>
Sweth: and to himſelff: and laſtly, what danger it ſhould breede, not only to himſelff and the kingdom off Sweth) but alſo, to all his neighbours, if in this haven, any neſt of Piraticall excurſion were ſetled, by the privat ambition of any whatſoever: he could no longer refuſe, by any, either meanes or equity, for the benefit off his Neighbours and friends, as alſo, off his own, and off the publick and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſecurity (in the meane time) to ſuccour and releve the oppreſſed, who ſo earneſtly intreated his help, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and Councell. By which his intention, Though this was effectuated, that the Emperiall Iniunctions did keepe their own authority, and the Baltick ſea ſhould be made ſecure for all Nations, who haue any intereſt the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin, and that the towne of Stralſovnd, by reaſon of the friendly intervention of his Ma. being freed from the Garriſons, off the moſt illuſtrious King off Denmark (as then hoſtile) ſhould be kept, both to its own liberty, and to the Empire of Rome, as the League, made with the towne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the ſame, doth yet clearly demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrate: Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, it was never a whit the more obtayned, that thoſe perturbers of peace, ſhould yet remit any thing of their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile attempts and purpoſes, but by occaſion theroff thay waxed more hot, in ſeeking the deſtruction therof, both by Lande and Sea: for finding themſelves to be fruſtrate of that haven, thay ſett vpon the haven of Wiſſmar and others: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being content with their own ſhipps, thay called from Danswijck, the Navie of the enimys of the kingdom of Sweth: into their ſociety, and thay began, ſo to annoy the ſea neare adioining, that his Ma. was at length forced (if he would have the ſea, and Commerce ſafe) to keepe them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo incloſed there by his Navie (and that, not without great expence and dammadg) vntill that, that yeare ſhould at length be expired ſecurely in ſom kinde.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding, that the moſt Illuſtrious king off
<pb facs="tcp:19684:5"/>
Sweth: might not herefore in any kinde remit his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and perpetual care for the peace, and common quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of theſe Nations; but rather that he might try all waies and meanes, to com to a friendly tranſaction: when he vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood that a treaty of peace was inſtituted at Lubeck betwixt the Roman Emperour and the king of Denmark, in the beginning of the yeare 1629. he thought it expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, to ſend his Ambaſſadors alſo thither in opportune time, that thay might both accommodat this matter of the towne of Stralſound, and compoſe all other Ielouſies, which were bred in theſe yeares, and that alſo (iff thay could help any thing therin) by their mediation thay might promove the treaty it ſelff to the wiſhed end: for thus he made account with himſelf, ſeeing that by occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion off that warr, which paſſed between the Romane Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, and the king off Denmark, many ſuchlike Iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies ſeemed to haue bin bredd, that neither peace could be concluded with the king off Sweth: Stralſound being excluded, neither could that towne be bound to any Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, it ſelf not being comprehended in the Treaty, by reaſon of the mutuall contracts, agreed vpon with that Citie concerning that matter.</p>
            <p>But howbeit the moſt Illuſtrious king off Denmark did thankfully admitt the Comming of the ſaid Ambaſſage; neither was the ſame with leſs courteſie and dece<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie deſired by letters from the other party; yet ſuch was the humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, wherwith he was requited, that his ſolemn Ambaſſage was not only not admitted, or at leaſt thought worthy off any anſwer, by letter; but alſo with great indignity repul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and commanded, to keepe not only from the towne off Lubeck, but alſo from the whole territory of Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, vpon hazard and threatning of extremity.</p>
            <p>Which only indignity, though in the Account off all Nations, it be allway eſteemed worthy of moſt iuſt revenge,
<pb facs="tcp:19684:6"/>
and there ſeemed no cauſe to remaine, why more rough remedies, ſhould be any longer abſtayned from: yet ſeeing the Deputies of the Emperour did at Length (in March, after that thay of Sweth: were recaled into the Kingdom againe) acknowledg the letters of the kings Ambaſſadg, by an Anſwer by letter, by which, as by way of excuſe, thay would ſeem to mollify the iniquity of the former ſentence; his Ma. alſo, in the meane time, eſteemed the ſame to have proceeded rather from ſome evill Councellers, then from publick Councell; neither did he yet ſuffer it to be ſuch, as might ſeem to be ſufficient, yea even ioyned with the reſt, to Committ his mutuall States to a iuſt warr, eſpecially ſeeing the ſaid deputies did withall ſignify, that thay had no power to treate with any other then the king of Denmark, yet thay knew certainly, that if the matter were yet referred, either to the Emperour himſelff, or to the Duke of Fridland, thay ſhould receiue an anſwer, which might give them content.</p>
            <p>It might now ſeem an vnworthie thing, to expoſe his patience any longer to ſuch ridiculous proceedings, it ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving alreadie bene wronged ſo many wayes: it being alſo very doubtfull, whither, or how, the matter might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by the party offended, to the imperour (with whom heretofore, no ſuch like communication had bene vſuall, to his Ma.) all wayes being prohibited in the whole Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Empire, and the treatie of Lubec drawing ſo neere an end: yet notwithſtanding, that no labour might be omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the deſired publick tranquillitie, and that no diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty might be any hinderance thervnto, all contrary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations being laid aſide, when the matter could not be related to the Emperour himſelf, his Ma. was at lenth, by the illuſtrous counſel of the Kingdom off Swethen indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, preſently in the month off April, not only to write to the Electorall convention, as being the cheif prop off the
<pb facs="tcp:19684:6"/>
Roman Empire, to which, theſe proceedings with forrain kings, were thought to be moſt diſpleaſing, and to ſue for op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune remedies; but alſo to give conſent, that a deputie, ſhould be withall ſent from the counſell, to the generall of the troups himſelf, who by his preſence might try, whither thoſe controverſies, which ſeemed to be bred betwixt the mutuall armies, might not be taken away by the Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſame; whervpon his Ma<hi rend="sup">s</hi>. Chamberlane the Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious L. Steno Bielke L. Baron, was preſently ſent to Kro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, with adjoined power, that, if he found the mynds of the contrary partie inclinable to peace, he ſhould conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te a ſtilſtand of armes for Stralſound, while that farder preparatories of treating being made, more commiſſioners might Follow, who might refer the whole buſines to a full tranſaction. But, when he, in the beginning of the ſpring aryved at Stralſound, and found the mynds of the adverſe party, and the whole face of the matter changed to the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, and that the former hoſtilities, were not only not taken away, but alſo augmented with freſh hoſtilities from day to day; as alſo Stralſound again to be aſſaulted, with divers onſets, all the havens of the coaſt to be armed, for to pray vpon the Swetian ſea; and which is the greateſt of all ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, that a compleat army was again privilie ſent to Pruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia, without any denunciation of warr, and that vnder the Emperours owne Marchall off the forces of Arnheimbia. this change did indeed, ſtay him from proceeding any farder, as it was fit; yet notwiſtanding, that he might in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure diſcharge his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion; he wrote to the Duke of Frid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, for what cauſes he was diſpatched, and having proteſted againſt the iniquitie of that armie, that was ſent over, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyred that both it, and all other hoſtilities might be ſtayed, iff the anſwere off the deputies of Lubec might other wayes ſeem to be ſincere: But the Duke of Fridla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d was ſo far, aither from recalling the army, or ſhewing any readines to treate:
<pb facs="tcp:19684:7"/>
with greater mocking, he confirmed his ſubdeputies anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers to be meerly ſcoffing, contending, that for this cauſe cheefly theſe ſouldiers could not be recalled, becauſe the Emperour had ſo many forces, that off neceſſitie he behoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, to diſburden himſelff off that army off arnheimbia, and therfore, he, not without cauſe, ſent it to his frend the King of Pole, againſt Swethen; as the authentike letters doe yet ſhew; neyther would he again anſwere any thing els to any purpoſe, to the reiterated deſires off the Ambaſſador; but cauſed the ſaid army to haſten its iorney; which alſo, the whole laſt ſommer, did vſe ſuch bitternes off fight in Pruſſia, againſt the King and Kingdom off Swethen; that, vules God, the Iuſt revenger off iniquitie, had made the recompence, off the attemps off their wicked intenſion to light vpon their owne heads, no ſmall daunger was like to have happened, both to the moſt Illuſtrious King, and Kingdom off Swethen, and to all his Ma<hi rend="sup">s</hi>. Frends.</p>
            <p>Can any man doubt therfore any longer, whither the moſt Illuſtrious King off Swethen had ſufficient cauſe, to move him, (all cogitations off peace laid aſide) long agoe to have taken armes, and prepared himſelf for warre, for the defence, off him, and his. But there was yet one thing reſtand, which ſeemed yet a litle to hinder the ſpeedy ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king off armes (to wit) the expectation of an anſwere to the Kings letters, from the Electorall convention, and the intervention off the moſt Illuſtrious King off Denmarck, who, at the perſwaſion off his Royall Ma. had from the laſt winter, even till now, begun to vrge the matter to trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: for certanly, ſo long as any ſufficient reparation off dammages and iniuries, and proviſion for the ſecuritie off his neighbours might be wrought by treatie, his Ma. was never ſo covetous off revenge, but that, for the zeale he bears to the common cauſe, and publict quietnes, he would willingly have ſuffered the matter to have bene en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, rather by treatie, then arms.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19684:7"/>But ſeing, that, from the beginning of Aprill, in this ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar 1630. when there was a day appointed for a convention at Dantſik in Pruſſia, vnto this very month of Iune, there is no ſignification of treatie made, by the partie offender, to the Commiſſarie of the partie offended, there preſent, and declaring by letters to Dantſik, his readines and power to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reate; how ſincerely the publict peace is deſired, it is eaſie hereby to be Iudged, eſpeciallie ſeing, their ſcoffings, not only of former times, but alſo after they had diſpatched their Commiſſaries to Dantſik (by poſſeſſing themſelvs of all fortified places and paſſages in Pomer, and preparing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves more eagerly to warr, then heretofore) doe plainly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſe, with what ſecuritie, any confidence may be put in ſuch like treaties.</p>
            <p>As for the Electorall convention; it might indeed have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one much in that matter, and his Royal Ma. perſwaded himſelf, it would ſo have done, if the States of the Empire, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad obtained the fredom of their auncient libertie, and if the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ower of evel willers had not taken ſuch root therein, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t ſeemed, to reiect all internall remedie. they of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention did alſo, in their anſwere (which was in the late month of Aprill conveighed to Stocholme) praiſe the pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceable intentions, and proffered tranſaction of the moſt Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious King of Swethen, offering Withall reciprocall frendſchip on their part. but ſeing they did not ſo much as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n a word, touch the remedies of the injuries done, which the Kings letters, did cheifly requires did they not leave it neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie for his Ma. to provide opportune remedies for himſelf.</p>
            <p>Wherfore ſeing ſo many, and waightie injuries ar really done to his Royall Ma. his letters intercepted, and opened: his ſubjects, ſervants and ſoudiers ſpoyled, and caried away into ſclavery; trade, naturally common, interdicted; the pole, his Ma<hi rend="sup">s</hi>. enemy, ſo often diſſwaded from peace; and a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable army led out into Pruſſia, for the ruinating of his Ma<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.
<pb facs="tcp:19684:8"/>
Kingdom off Swethen. again alſo not graunting the King off Swethen, ſo much, as ſafe paſſage, yea, his Frends, neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and kindred (for malice towards him) oppreſſed, ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led off their dominions, and only not altogether extirpated, the ſuers for peace (contrary to the cuſtome off barbarians) ignominiouſly rejected; and at laſt, a hoſtile army twice ſent againſt his Ma. and that without any cauſe, or pretext? Doe not all theſe, yea each off them (by conſent off all Nations, by perſwaſion off reaſon, nature it ſelf inſtigating therto) deſerve a moſt due revenge, except due reparation doe interceed. ſeing ſo many threatnings, ſo great preparations, ſo many divices, ar as yet manifeſted, to the reproach off all the balthike havens, and off the very ſea it ſelf, by which, all both deſignes, deeds and determinations, ſeem everie where, both by ſea and land, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpire for his Ma<hi rend="sup">s</hi>. ruine? doe they not caſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him (though vwilling) the right of defence, that at leaſt, according to the cuſtome of warr, and by the law off all nations, he may procure the moderation off a bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meles protection? ſeing, he having tryed all the wayes off law, no more equitable remedies ar graunted? yea ſeing ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilitie is everie where offered; doth not the verie law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture require, that force be repelled by force.</p>
            <p>Since therfore there reſts no other meane to procure ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetie, then that his Ma. according to God, doe help the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie off himſelf and his, by armes; he thought good by the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, tot let the Chriſtian wordle Iudge, by what merit of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and how ſore againſt his will, he is redacted to theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremeties. it is true, the defence only of the citie of Stral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound, is pretended for the ambition of moſt avaricious men: but how they them ſelves, by inferring off ſo many former hoſtilities, and how, afterward (as it is ſaid) love off the common ſecuritie, and ſo many reaſons, have provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked his Royall Ma. theſe have expreſſed, to the good off the Roman Empire it ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19684:8"/>Iff at any other tyme, he had aided the enemies off the Emperour, or the Roman Empire, or made any leauge with their enimies againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or at leaſt put any other advice or counſel in executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to their prejudice; no man might won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at their diffidence, and retaliation of ſom kind of reven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge flowing from hence? Now, ſeing ſuch hath alwayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the conſtancie off his peaceable determination, that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ath not only kept inviolated Freindſhip and neutralitie during all this German warr; but hath neither before, nor after the ſame, given any Iuſt pretext, of offence; he can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot, but, with moſt iuſt greeff complain before all the word<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, off ſo great an indignitie.</p>
            <p>Wherfore, as his Royall Ma. doth ptoteſt, that theſe his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rmes, ar not as yet prepared, to any prejudice off the Roman <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mpire (with which he hath no inimitie) but only to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rotection off himſelf, and his, vntil ſuch time, as his Frends <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd neighbours be put in the ſame cace, in the which all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he neighbourhood, hath before this warr, peaceably flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed ſo long time; and vntill cheifly the citie off Stral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound, the balthik ſea, and the Kingdom of Swethen may promiſe vnto themſelves heerafter, more certan ſecuritie: ſo he maketh no doubt, but that the impartiall reader, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he verie ſafetie of Nations, will improve and deteſt ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitable proceedings off the contrarie party, as they have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſerved; and he doth certanly hope, that all equitable Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans and all the Chriſtian wordle, will favour this his innocencie, and Iuſt cauſe of taking ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, aiming at the lawfull ſtaying off ſo vnjuſt perſecution.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
